Samuel L. Belcher Collection
Samuel L. Belcher Collection
1991-2008
Belcher, Samuel L.
.75 linear ft.
Biographical material, patent information, and product data related to Samuel Belcher's innovations in blow molding.
3647874
Biographical History
Samuel L. Belcher (1933-2009) was an American plastics inventor and entrepreneur, especially noted for his many innovations in plastic blow-molded packaging.
He began his career with Rubbermaid, Inc. and later worked for Owens-Illinois and Wheaton Industries. He was Product Manager of Container Machinery for the U.S. Plastics Machinery Division of Cincinnati Milicron. He was president of his consulting firm, Sabel Plastechs of Moscow, Ohio, from 1987 until 2009
Among his technical achievements are the first PET bottle with an integrated handle, which he patented and licensed to Mitsubishi of Japan; the first flip-top, living-hinge closure for liquid detergent bottles, patented at Owens-Illinois; the McDonald's foam clamshell package, patented at Owens-Illinois in 1974; the first injection blow molding machine for PET bottles, developed while Director of Research at Wheaton; and the plastic spice turntable, the largest volume single item ever produced by Rubbermaid.
In all he developed 54 patents. Belcher edited the volume Practical Extrusion Blow Molding (New York: Marcel Dekker, 1999) and authored Practical Guide To Injection Blow Molding (CRC Press, 2007). Belcher was inducted into the Plastics Hall of Fame in 2003.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Samuel L. Belcher Collection consists of biographical material, subject files, videotapes and writings.
Biographical material contains information about Samuel Belcher’s career and awards he received.
Subject files contains one blueprint drawing of a Beta II Process machine, patent information on the PET bottle with handle, and photographs of various machines and products.
Videotapes contains tapes from various companies about machines and processes.
Writings contains texts and illustrations of presentations given at ABC conferences in 2007, 2008 and 2009.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Separated Material
Twelve plastics artifacts donated with the collection have been transferred to the
Plastics Artifacts Collection
.
One book by Belcher has been transferred to general collections for cataloging. Issues of the Society of Plastics Engineers Blow Molding Division Newsletter from 1983-2004 (incomplete run) were transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Plastics; Business and Industry; Belcher, Samuel L., 1933-; Automa s.p.a.; Cincinnati Milacron, Inc.; FGH Systems, Inc.; Graham Engineering Corporation.; Jackson Machinery, Inc.; Mag-Plastic.; Owens-Illinois, inc.; Plastics Hall of Fame.; Rubbermaid Incorporated.; Sabel Plastechs, Inc.; Society of Plastics Engineers.; Society of Plastics Engineers -- Blow Molding Division.; Engineers -- United States.; Blow Molding.; Plastics in packaging.; Plastics industry and trade -- United States.; Plastics machinery industry -- United States.; Plastics machinery.; Plastics industry and trade -- Equipment and supplies.; Polyethylene terephthalate.; Articles.; Brochures.; CD-ROMs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Design patents.; Drawings (visual works); DVDs.; Photographs.; Videotapes.; Engineers.; Entrepreneurs.; Inventors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Donna Belcher, 2011.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Awards, 1995-2008; certificates and information regarding Belcher's receipt of various industry awards (Box 1)
  - Plastics Hall of Fame, 2003; papers and articles about Belcher's induction into Plastics Hall of Fame (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2006 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Blow molding calculator, calculator and trouble shooting guide from Quantum Chemical Company 1995 (Box 1)
  - Drawing: beta II process (Box 1)
  - Patent for PET bottle with handle, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of machinery and products (Box 1)
- Videotapes, Titles and information about videotapes is copied verbatim from printed and handwritten labels on the items.
  - Automa s.p.a. fully automatic blow molding machines, Plus at 0.7D – plus at 2D – Plus at 2DD – plus at 5 – plus at 5D – plus at 2D co-optionals (Box 2)
  - Automa s.p.a. fully automatic blow molding machines, Injection stretch-blow moulding machines – model: NSB 20 (Box 2)
  - Cincinnati Milacron, cyclone accumulator head; rapid color change, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Cincinnati Milacron, eclipses E-75 polycarbonate production, VT 6300-099, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Cincinnati Milacron, tracker “keeping your process on track, VT 6300-157 (Box 2)
  - Cincinnati Milacron, T-series large part appls., 1997; Combo tape of: T-1100 vertical clamp/35lb. accumulator head (55 gallon drum production), includes VT-6300-165 T-series flat, VT-6300-170 (Box 2)
  - FGH Systems, Inc., b&w 40, b&w 6000DE, b&w 8000DE (Box 2)
  - Graham Engineering Corporation: accumulator dead update, blow molding machines (Box 2)
  - Jackson Machinery, Inc. fleximatic trimming wheels (Box 2)
  - Jackson Machinery, Inc. fleximatic toner bottles (Box 2)
  - Mag-Plastic: 2 stage process (Box 2)
  - Sabel hand over hand PET bottle machine, 1997 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Conference presentations, 2007-2009; includes CD-Rs of powerpoints "Where are we going? up or down," (2007) and "What can we do to cut costs and improve the bottom line?" (2008). (Box 1)